right Michael thanks so much for this
opportunity to talk to you and I really
must say that that your work on LED
systems goes back a long way with me
like I was a long haired hippie and a VW
band trying driving of Europe visiting
eco communities when I first read about
your work so um this is a long time ago
and but I feel like right now that's
that's why I'm so glad that we had this
opportunity to talk today and we are
already seeing in the in the wake of
kovat 19 and the cascading synchronous
failure that is now rippling across the
globe we're seeing supply lines fail
we're seeing that local communities like
how brittle that that global economy was
or is how supply like just-in-time
production on the other side of the
globe basically leaves you extremely
vulnerable to any kind of disruption and
this is what's happening all over and at
the same time over the last 10 years
lots of organizations have started to
home in on the bio regional scale being
the scale where we can actually rematch
the human impact and presence on earth
in a way that we are less of a
degenerated and more of a regenerative
species and whether we're lucky enough
that this global monster of of a
degenerative economy actually has
another 10 years so we have a bit of a
software preparation of what's coming
there are more pandemics and more
climate change disruption on the way in
any case we need to prepare the kind of
regional exchange systems that you have
been working with for what 40 years by
now or 30 at least or 38 and a half okay
so I would love to just just basically
quietly listen to your wisdom of what
you would suggest and people can do and
if you want we've just talked a little
bit privately on my project in Majorca
if you want to make it concrete Majorca
but but you can talk about in general I
think what what you're offering is
something that community
is everywhere could really learn from so
and over to you
well thank you Daniel thank you very
much generous and accurate summary of
much of my long history and a hippies
traveling around the world and he W by
season would like but we've all brought
up a lot in the last decades
particularly last few years and these
days I'm focusing particularly on
biomimicry circularity and
responsibility accountability yeah the
island thing for instance you know at
the beginning of my exploration of these
issues I was coming across the what is
the island economy what if the
comparative advantage of get your stuff
from out there export the other you know
import/export from the island and it's
very dangerous stuff you start importing
stuff from other parts of the world well
any slightest idea of how it was made
what it was made from the consequences
of the process how many intermediaries
were involved in this then the other and
we also export without the slightest
idea of what we're doing with basic
resources our futures our histories or
whatever and in a way an island and an
archipelago should be responsible for it
it puts out in the world and what it
takes in from the world so increasingly
we've got this
what is our self-reliance it's not about
self isolation it's not like our Island
nothing else out there
well it's about responsible contribution
input output transit balance and we're
sending people stuff they need are we
responding to them and a useful way that
builds the Commonwealth of the
archipelago the whole or is it just the
idiot event you know idiot and the sort
of Greek sense of this self-interested
in comparison to the citizenship the
idiot is is
hopefully reasonable I'm looking after
read me myself my family my business my
tribe my territorial thing the nation
state the fronts my hey where as a
citizen behavior is the same person
whose activities somehow relate to the
whole of the agencies of their space and
then there's this whole circular economy
stuff yeah you know referring to Ellen
MacArthur Foundation brilliant work and
terrific stuff over told heavenly
oversold heavily Hadley oversold and
under under considered under critical
but it's held they've got a lot of
attention they've got a lot of support
where the circularity they're
circulating materials
what about circulating money is it not a
recognizable process that when I buy a
hat from you you give me the Hat and I
give you the money so the two things go
in different directions
and in fact as regards our economic
engine if money moves and stuff goes
we've got a patterning between the money
and the stuff so if the money can go
those places well the goods went those
places too right you know transfers the
alien who looks at us from the upper
stratosphere sees people move in and
doing things but if they had a monetary
model they'd see the same pattern of
money moving and doing things in the
opposite direction that you are bangin
on top here this is really interesting
because it also like the terms of Reve
regionalizing and re localizing like
what my big critique of the aisle and
make our foundations work on circular
economy as much as I really appreciate
that they have pushed it hugely and I'm
not wanting to be negative about them
the thing that there's an oversell comes
from McDonald's days of cradle-to-cradle
of this notion of upcycling it's
physically impossible to 100% recycle
most of the minerals that we build our
technology out of and you know you would
need free energy to do so anyway and no
such there's free energy drinks right
free love it always cost me in the long
run this article basically you end up
with running the system bound over a
longer period of time that's one thing
and the other thing is that while they
drew so much from the early industrial
ecologists they actually if you look at
the kind of early areas and these guys
they pointed out that the most efficient
cycle is the shortest cycle the local
cycle and you mustn't get into the game
of the longer cycles if you can never
avoid it and that I'm just sensing
that's a needed to also that the money
and community well it is I mean money is
the social medium and we talk about
Twitter or Facebook or whatever on the
internet connecting and disconnecting is
whatever but look at the event patterns
that are determined by the social medium
called money and how it in my view has
colonized their communities
basically you come in with guns and day
flags and germs that gives you
territorial advantage and then you nail
it down with the money because that
gives you trading control so the money
becomes the import-export carrier you
really to take Michael Hudson's analysis
of the banking system has perfect
parasite it infects you without you
noticing it takes over your major
processes and eventually convinces you
brain that it's an essential part of the
entire system but it is the host and
you're privileged to be taking part in
it
well the banking system has done that to
us and we believe money as though money
is a thing that is not within our
our grasp our choice our autonomous
development ultimately circular money
for money to be circular to me means
that I have to be the issuer of the
promise that circulates within that
network of people who believe any sense
of that and returns for me to service
any money which is merely a coin or a
token or a bank issue to tax credit or
whatever is not my money if I have that
in my bank it's their money in my bank I
say it's their money in their bank write
anything I see on my screen about my
bank balances my score in their casino
where they make the rules when they take
a cut of just everything moves by that's
for your Margaret Kennedy and excellent
very strong on me the banking system is
a an overall drag on the interest
structures or whatever but it's not just
the interest in fact the interest is
only symptomatic it's the scarcity and a
token that I hold because I needed it
and when I spend it it's gone and that's
the characteristic of their money when
you spend it is gone say goodbye so
their money ain't your money and it's
gone your money is your promise which is
a relationship deal with in the others
in your network and as you make a
promise it causes turbulence in that
cloud of behavior and then somebody
wants to hire you because the money is
in your loop and of course the smaller
the loops the tighter the reference and
reciprocity also the limited variety
there may not be a neurosurgeon in your
street this is the classic critique when
when people mention late systems there's
always well as the aroma therapist and
the massage there I mean how exactly
that sentence about let's but there's a
bread and beer if you don't have bread
and you don't have a beer you don't have
and metaphorically I don't like it so
that there has to be bread and circuses
people have to be entertained and
satisfied but needs have to be met so
it's gotta be supermarkets and cafes
have you found or have you what is the
minimal viable size of a system like
that at a sort of community regional
scale in terms of the requisite variety
of like I don't know if they's if it's
just numbers correlating to the
diversity in general or whether you
could say sometimes you have very
diverse networks with fewer people do
you know anything about we used to think
that the minimum scale was about 50
small businesses that would provide
enough confidence of inter trading
between the businesses for them to open
the trading model through to the general
public who are both their customers and
their staff so if you have 50 businesses
with the staff of 50 business being the
customers at 49 you know and said you've
got a cross relationship between all the
the businesses and all the people to
different class groups to make it work
effectively we went through the third
party which was the charities because
people don't trust business and business
and trust people so we have this model
of the businesses issue money to the
charities community groups confer
service upon them and then Joe public
buys the money I should change his money
with the charity so I put hard cash into
the charity and I get a dollar I can
spend in my favorite restaurant charity
business whatever you know the issuer's
of the money it's like yeah I don't know
if you know the Rotary Club auction
model all the businesses put up things
that we have a party and we all bid on
those things and the cash goes the
beneficiary the charity and I get
whatever it was well that's a standard
model for pumping revenue into a
beneficiary and leaving the beneficiary
unintel does
very important part of that little bit
is that the beneficiary doesn't or the
business it donated to it all the person
who changed it into a cash flow for
beneficiaries off the hook as the
concept we call Co vestment that comes
in later don't lose it Co hasn't it's
not investment it's Co vestment because
it's to two entities reconciling in
their mutual support of something so
that it's off and flying and they're in
a loop it's the creation of the loop
that's the critical thing take smith the
isle of Guernsey to remember the end of
Guernsey I know where there's roughly on
the map but I don't you can basically
throw a stone to France in the Normandy
region and in the 1820s because it was
technically English it was a bit of a
problem for the French and vice-versa so
they weren't getting much business and
life was tough on guarantee and they
decided in some respect to build a stock
house on the dock you know they needed a
place to shelter the travelers coming in
and out all that so they so they
invested in building the stock house but
run under money halfway through it in a
crazy fit of genius they created stock
certificates paid the continuing work on
the project in those certificates so the
job got done the people got paid and the
certificates circulated for next 60
years there's an economic engine in the
community that was the Guernsey money it
was beautiful I mean the stock house was
good it did shelter it was an
infrastructure event that was real and
significant but there was far more
significance in these pieces of paper
which by their circulation must have
created many many times the value when I
lived that hint on the local sort of
it's not quite a community bank it's
it's it's a co-op a copia issued the
local currency and people could invest
into the local community on wind farm
through that currency and then that
kinda circulated in this
in being a place where because it
equable printed we also always had this
added effect that about every year about
2,000 pounds worth of it would go as
memorabilia for tourists I've been to
Finland and this is one of their 10
notes and and it actually made extra
money and I know it's just like Disney
dollars it's they walk off with the
money and leave you with trinkets it's
over your thing but taking that model
down to its nuts and bolts hmm
consider a local patreon where you had a
local resource board of projects that
needed support wind farms music students
a senior's resort or whatever like you
have a serious possibilities which are
already invested by local businesses
with credits and then when you put cash
into this thing you get the credits so
you can go shopping right so you don't
lose anything by supporting the local
musician or the venture development or
the whatever because although you
partner with hardend cash which you need
you get credits which you can then spend
and create the circulation now that's
the core of this concept we call Co
vestment and use it to legitimize
businesses now the curious thing in
these currency systems is that you and I
as human beings are entitled to issue
promises
there's we're real people when we exist
businesses however are zombies they have
no presence no character they live
entirely on one feed stock it's called
money they don't need air they don't
they don't need a damn thing if the
money is flowing so they tend to a
fairly particular attitude towards money
which is they want it and they want to
be real careful about how much of it you
have so they tend to be pretty tight
with the customers and pretty tight with
her stuff too you can both of them are
drains from the
retained earnings of the business so if
you want to start a currency what you
have to do is find out that the
customers and the staff of a given
business like the idea of participating
in these circulatory looks that support
the development of common and we've got
it in our community with this this fiber
which is a five dollar bill the QR code
on the bank that references what it's
all about and you get this in our local
pub by going to the jar on the counter
which has a notice Alan says we're
supporting the farm rescue fund if you
want to support them put cash in here
for them take out one of these coupons
come to the bar and buy beer now what
that does in one quick movement it takes
what we used to think we needed some
twenty businesses and half a dozen
charities and local-level reduces it to
one jar on the bar and printing the
money so your question about what's the
smallest viable unit one any single
business with an aspiration to social
support can capitalize that project by
conferring its promise every time on to
that project the body shop for instance
used to give its staff two hours every
Friday afternoon to help out but it
doesn't help out they define far better
to give coupons to the charities and
have that trade round so that's our
basic model create the money buy
business promise because business
promises what people believe in but hold
on I think I'm trying to get my head
around this and the the buyer has
costs to the beer like I buy either it
makes the beer that has a certain post
or it buys the beer and yeah these are
for the mark-up cost over its markup
over costs is the the range in which
community currencies can operate
effectively it's you see the the essence
of what a physical human community is is
value added by our time knowledge
service interaction our monetary model
includes import costs and export costs
and taxes and all this stuff in the
money and no business can go a hundred
percent into a community currency
because it would have a huge cash
consequence but any restaurant can say
50 percent cash 50 percent in the
community money a grocery store might
say 80 percent cash 20 percent in the
community money right and a street
entertainer like you and myself can go
hundred percent right because you know
and it's subject to tax issues of course
because it's an income and unless you
couldn't run it off it lets take me to
your example example did and people
would take a fiver and then give it back
to the bar so that that actually that
note immediately back out of circulation
no it puts it into circulation what it
is done is it's given the business you
seen business I can just print the money
there's like hyman minsky code I'm
immensely was a Chicago economists but a
good one
which is a very rare thing and he said
anybody can create money that's an easy
part the hard part is getting others to
accept it right that applies to
businesses particularly if a business is
to print off bunches of money and say
give it to the staff instead of wages
and they're in court there's legislation
about something if a business prints
lots of money and puts it in the
newspaper is treated like a discount
coupon on trash the business cannot
infer value in it all
tokens of promise unless it makes it
real by putting the value to the charity
redeeming it and then these bills in
their till are actually money so the
business instead of being single
threaded with a cash in cash out cash in
cash a continual vertical flow of money
in into the bucket money out of gone
it's now got this other money that it
puts out and it circulates in the plane
of the community and returns to income
so it's got the positive activities
actually the money is sort of siphoned
off it is and then the charity does what
for example just well the cash its fans
that's what it means the cash form
charities need that if you won't
remember and so there are many colonies
are a community it's just not thought of
cash flow and this we can connect to
those but principally the consequences
it involves this flying we love if I
give there's a playground swing and
every time you go past it you're
accelerating the spins of the kids so we
can have a significant impact on local
well this whole colvett thing and the
panics people are getting into with
monetary they realize it's not just a
supply of goods for sure and it's a
supply of money and what do you know the
supply of money seems to be very
important to everything this is the
lesson from from Argentina and all these
these big collapses that it's not just
like when you don't have money that's
worth anything anymore then then nobody
can exchange goods and services that the
goods and services are there yeah
although as Olaf Daniel oral office
often said this isn't a problem in
Russia Russians don't expect anything so
when the shit hits the fan they've got
stuff under the floorboards and they all
know each other and there's a nun's for
not going on because networks are there
but in the Western world the networks
have been shredded by the nuclear
economic unit you're looking after
yourself we give you money you'd spend
it and sure autonomy so we defend money
and we defined
like in this current situation when you
when you think of communities really
everywhere global north and global south
beginning to seriously think how do we
avoid being quite so fragile in the
future and how would we regionalize our
not initially our economy through
through these kind of systems but
eventually also our assistance of
production and consumption and create
more diverse regional economies and one
of the things that I learned from you
mentioned him earlier banal Yatta
is that he always told me that the best
thing would be to have an ecology of
money systems you just also should every
business needs to also still trade in
the international currency and only can
take percentages of the local currency
so which particular models would you say
people should look into as they're
looking into creating more diverse local
and regional currencies and for example
the like in an early exchange we
mentioned the Swiss year system which is
more into business currency and it's
counter cyclical so if there if if Swiss
alone is really doing well in the global
casino game then the veer almost
disappears and when Switzerland has a
problem then the via comes back up and
yeah which systems do you think are
particularly I I'm a believer in variety
variety in the sense of ashbey's laws of
variety and systems theory that the
complexity of that which you are engaged
with and your tools for engaging those
through complexity should match variety
matching it used to be used to sail a
ship by telling the guy beside you to
move the wheel but you don't fly an
airplane by the time the game is find
you to move the stake you know the rate
of complexity is different we've got an
economy in the world which is totally
inappropriate for a singular money now
you know I don't have to argue
particularly what's right or wrong about
sinking money in some ways
the conventional single money is a very
successful tool does exactly does it
competes of fuck out of it all puts its
all of us on the treadmill
hallelujah run or die die die so it's
very successful in its way but it leaves
a big gap which is is that all we got
can we also have these networks of
neighbourhood with without fighting it
don't don't get in the way of the
locomotive let's start these networks of
interaction and exchange in society
community and many of them not one it's
been the biggest problem all the way
through the development of LED systems
was always a plural word by the way LED
systems from 1983 was plural I think we
couldn't get anybody to go plural in
their systems they wanted to do one and
to get it right
so they'd and that meant that they set
up a committee and a group and rewrite
all and you've got to think about can
about personal money issuing in these
circles so when I spend money it's like
my level was down because I'm pumping
and everybody's going up a little bit
and so the whole cloud run and then that
percolates so somebody spends money so
think of a smoke ring right so your
orange smoke ring for instance is your
region and it's got 10,000 people in it
in businesses and your training in that
is substantial and in the businesses and
it's of its own nature but there's also
your locality a thousand people and
that's another little green cloud which
is in the same place it's just sometimes
you're singing green and sometimes
you're singing or and all of them have
this resurgence recirculation effect in
them which is not controlled so some of
these are time banks in my neighborhood
a time bank you know 20 people or a
childcare balancing act so it's not
about having the currency it's about
having the opportunity to have as many
currencies for my expression and count
you should as I'm deal with and play
with
this is this is a key point there and
because I'm just wondering whether it
takes a special sort of person know who
is kind of the of the frugal type and
the systemic understanding type that
says well I really want to support my
local community and it all makes sense
and so they have this wallet which they
have like their normal County and they
have that one and then I have that one
and because it's a bit complicated when
I have to make the mentally ready
how do you get around that well um I
mean there's so many parts in that in a
way first of all the the if you have to
bills to $10 $20 52 identical bills and
for some reason you've made a mark on
one and that one when you spend it
somehow rather it will come back this
one never will you know this one when
you spend it it's a goner right this one
might which we spend first along they
might come back yeah they're yeah you
made the decision so for instance your
your your swipe card your you tap and
pay in your local community will then
have the ability to take what the
merchant is offering as a range of six
currencies the immersion is taking over
my original he's taking this is taking
that he's taking he's taking the local
Chinese festival network currencies you
know whatever like because what's not to
take it so Archer will be open to many
and it will have a point-of-sale system
you'll just tap the guy who has to do
the accounting of that at the end of the
day might just say good as can we just
stick with one no that's a trouble if
you if you think you have to do
accounting it's because you're working
in scarcity and
you've gotta watch it I've got to make
sure the rent doesn't come to you before
my paycheck it's you know that that's
management of money in our singular
money in a multiple money it's like
you're supported by all these little
balloons that it's just and you know the
trouble with them local money isn't
earning it it's spending remember but
yeah it's because because by comparison
every desperate for cash so you offer
them the local and then tomorrow or
whatever there's a less urgency no
compulsion in community money compulsion
in the main track so in the spending
level it's tricky unless I know I can
get 20% of my groceries with this money
I get 50% in any restaurant there's
money it works in my consumer goes to 30
40 %
I'm getting my massages done and then
all of a sudden you see these options
opening up and why not service that
don't worry in all the communities I
lived in that had an LED system and it a
light system remember that singular a
LED system - but usually one of them is
not working well and it is true that
that basically normally I don't treat
myself to massages or those kind of
things because they expensive compared
to like if I have to not put cash on
that where else - like I always look at
it I don't know if you use an hour so
yeah so but but but it is in terms of
making it operational for at that
regional scale yes well that is the
technology and that's why we're did you
ever hear about the Irish Bank strike no
classic in the 70s there was a bank
strike in Ireland about 72 or 73 where
the clearing house in the middle of
somewhere Dublin like yes or somewhere
where all the banks clearly checked they
struck and so the banks couldn't
reconcile there were local accounts you
know what paper was and what
so that to close their doors so nobody
can get cash now in France this happened
and it closed down France my
brother-in-law was driving to Zurich to
get his pay he had to go there to get
cash to come back to buy bread you know
so France froze the Irish on the other
hand just started writing checks to each
other hmm
so if I had to pay for some Android a
check you see and you put it in your
wallet and you had a wallet that was
that thick with bits of paper and all
sorts of things that you were using them
to pay off other people well that was
the first phase and it worked that it
was stiff the second phase of the strike
because it lasted two months broke and
then restarted the second phase one for
about nine months I believe and what was
happening was that certain employers
were paying their their paychecks non
cash because he didn't have it nobody
had cash so they had to pay man a
paycheck but rather make it 147 pound
they do five checks of 20 hmm
vortex of ten and the leaders in this
were the brewing industry it silent
natural and it was I ask this in Dublin
when I speaking one time in the room
just went crazy for ten minutes nobody
would shut up they were all chattering
and raving about it because it had been
the best year they'd had in the
seventies it had more fraud and
bankruptcy than any other year in that
than that cycle and everybody just had a
great ongoing party high liquidity high
localization high security when you know
where you can spend it what's the
problem at a in it so you've got to set
up that that cycle of acceptance why not
hmm why not you know and and when it
comes to the wine not all of it
people can drop their reservations quite
easily now yes it will start with the
conscious they awake they aware the
intent the purpose for the bioregion
list the three keys the Paramount's the
permaculture people have got to be
yes no Mollison was very keen on this
one stage and tried to send two people
up to study it the only people ever came
to actually study this system for most
really I still wonder what it is that
like for example here may occur um
Inka had the terrain one one town one of
the not the biggest but one of the
bigger towns had the towering local
currency and Palma still has the Palmer
hours which are kind of more like the
Ithaca hours a time back the cash factor
no and that but all these systems are
sort of people use them but it's it's
really fringe it's there's no there's no
bang for the buck there's no purpose in
it there's no experience of benefit but
if you're say a small business is trying
to rebuild after a problem or and
startup artist whatever and it's a
question of staff and customers if you
could put together something that was
enthusiastically supported by the
customers and the staff why not so
tonight I just had an idea to help me
think through this and yeah Majorca we
we have the problem that basically
tourism just fight and that's not a
problem it's not a problem for the
planet and one less one less thing to
worry about and but at the same time
that's easily set on an island where 80%
of the tourism and they have really good
people looking at their children and
kind of going what am I going to do now
and we all yeah and and and so some
people make promises of agua will
recover it and will own shit and all
that but the jury is still out on how
deep this crisis will bite and how I
think we're all ready most people are
now understanding it will not be a
bounce-back we will not get to what we
had before and that that's a probably a
good thing
but if I now think of the future here in
Majorca where the government is already
talking about creating a basic income
like universal basic income and rather
than having these people wait until the
bars open again so they can be a waiter
again and if local land owners in local
farmers and what would basically offer
people a currency to go out for two days
or three days a week spend some time in
the drum and Tanner build up these
beautiful stone walls there's therefore
20,000 kilometres of dry stone wall on
my own that's halfway around the world
three times as long as the Great Wall of
China and so much to be done over a long
period of time and there takes them it's
a beautiful thing to do it's hard work
but it's it's rewarding and how would
you see a system okay if that then
bought them local food well the the
matter that I'm recommending at this
point or drafting round and recommending
because I mean tell me much about it is
that governments are offering quick
fixes and loans lot of small businesses
are invited to take up loans in Canada
you're inviting 30 $40,000 with long
with the expectation that a component
will be forgivable or will get the rest
later hmm do I want to take on a $30,000
loan in my business at this point it's
gonna is you know I can't paint now
won't be able to pay a fee or so so my
suggestion is take the loan and then put
the money in a bank account in common
with 20 other businesses and use that as
the backing for a standard cash back
currency nice one that is a good idea
it's just yeah notes are available all
over Europe already it's a community
that's a really nice idea because we
know that the businesses are keen on a
cash back currency I mean even in
Bristol
yeah versus they say it's no use but we
take it finally take it because if they
don't take it the customer goes
somewhere else do they take it and they
just take it straight to the bank and
get their ninety five pence in the pound
you know so you don't think it's good
they just have to use it yeah and they
willing to use it because they know
there's a cash backing on the full
invoice the full acceptance now if you
want people to just go for this and take
it for granted and see it as part of the
thing then full acceptance
bing-bong and the means of doing it like
we can do with our software prints the
money basically these days but so does
any ticketing system and you can do it
all on accounts you know you can set up
a swipe or a switch or a tap or and it
was no trouble these days I mean this is
a lot of the things I'm really focusing
on it more there's two aspects to my
strategy one is essentially we're all we
could all use a money that helped us out
in addition to the shit that goes
through you know we know this stuff
we're surviving it if we can or not why
not have this as well you know it's not
an acceptable I'm going to everybody was
acceptable - enough that you can
generate the concept and whatever lot's
of luck my friend but the pervasiveness
of this oh yeah there's got to be
unthought it's like when you get people
on a bicycle first if they thought about
getting on the bicycle they wouldn't I
mean it's difficult obviously gonna fall
over of fries hard maybe it'll stay in a
line or something you when they get on
the bicycle and move to get it so
they've got to be given a currency that
they don't think about but we just fits
in usefully and creates circularity
sorry I know I just I just had another
fault but then I already had the father
of white my book works well anymore but
it would have worked brilliantly before
on the basis of what you just said well
okay we have this special thing actually
lots of people have these tourist tax in
local tourist
and and and so basically people arrived
they've paid for their hotels but then
when they arrive at the hotel they're
all asked to pay another dollar fifty or
euro fifty and that then becomes part of
what's called the Eco tax which
supposedly is invested in sustainable
things around the island but if if they
had or if they in the future even in the
reduced tourism that we might get in the
future and would take that money and
directly put it into such a cash back
fund for been a much more agile local
currency you'd multiply the money coming
in massively it's not just multiply its
capture it's like the swales you know if
you're in a permaculture you've got a
watershed wash off and so you build
banks and you try and catch the water
they know it so well when people talk
about capturing or multipliers with
conventional money i I just disregard
that because frankly it's like a spin
dryer the money goes around every time
it's spent
it's sheds food cost of goods tax
whatever and so money is not containable
conventional money you're not
containable but when you have a local
currency it doesn't have a multiplier
effect it is a persistence effect it
doesn't multiply it just is slow it
spread it synced proponents what water
mantra actually works for money - yes
yes in place you looted and it still can
have it and having it is is this is the
Commons of money this is free speech
these are our ability to declare our
money by our promise and our fulfillment
one thing past you that it's it's an
idea that I had just after I published
my book and then for a number of reasons
because I'm not that geeky and I hate
accounting and I had bureaucracy I I
never really pushed that I pursued it
but I I talked to a lot of people that I
believe some of them kind of ran with
power of the idea which is great that
was the the intention and basically
and and it might be flawed but here's
the idea I was sort of thinking how
would we if the current monetary system
is built on a zero-sum game that needs
winners and losers that that needs us to
exploit each other and exploit the
planet for the whole thing to keep going
the hole in build growth imperative in
the economy and all that how would we
create money that is truly regenerative
in the kind of biological ecological
regeneration kind of way and Link it to
it like and it's going to take me about
two minutes and then you the fraud was
the following would it be possible to
create a bio productivity backed
currency that would ultimately function
to pay anybody who is a farmer or a
forester twice not just for what they're
extracting from the land in terms of
produce timber or produce but em they
would also be paid for being guardians
of the landscape for bringing carbon
back into the ground and basically
carbon sequestration the thief would
ultimately as they can demonstrate that
they've been drawing down carbon
successfully in regenerating land
thereby increasing a real value then
this real value would become the backing
of that currency i I called it the
region back back then and I say I
believe that there's a number of people
like the regen network that are now
playing with something very similar but
they're doing it with with a kind of
blockchain I mean that's another
conversation I think of the weird finger
pedals right pedals in a bicycle one and
then the other the result you're looking
for get it the other way around it's by
the act of recirculation that you create
the Commonwealth where that bio regional
capital
build up naturally the the the patterns
of connection are that's the real thing
years ago and it's is that
interconnectivity and activity that
lifts all those bolts hmm okay now you
can place an incentive you can say we're
going to value this community's
bioregional assets or our indigenous
rights god damn it
native groups talking about using their
indigenous rights as the basis for a
blockchain yeah well we're valuable
therefore we'll issue money and then of
course the money as you by the short
hair so you lose your shirt on your
money so the difficulty that people have
is will create a money and make him an
incentive for something you've got to
have the things happening that make the
money the realization of that it's a
it's a chicken-egg consequence they're
not chicken and eggs there's a chick in
the middle
so things were three ways it's ABC right
I'm a great believer in triples by the
way the naps in Christ nothing in pairs
pairs are to Bible singular is
non-existent so the first rational
behavior is with triples I do something
for him so they do something for you so
you do something for me and that's clean
this is where I'm you know I really
respect so much of what Charles
Eisenstein says but wish he would get
his pattern down mmm
like the gift to be persistent must have
equality of acknowledgment and recording
otherwise pay it forward is pay it away
it just dissipates outwards there's no
patterning the the patterning of mutual
commitment notice I dropped mutual
credit mutual credit is a dangerously
misconceived it tries people's heads who
is giving credit to whom for what so you
commitment however it's the same process
plus and minus in the ledger you decide
your Ledger's you dissociate with them
it's like a Google Group bang here's
your network now we've been advocating
for this multiplicity of instant
creation of currencies we've got the
technology for it it's crude but it
works it's an API and we want to take it
up through the market now we realized
with this business your paper money that
is cheap easy and would be effective if
energy behind it but it's also possible
to go to a larger scale so for instance
we're looking at a group called Mac in
Canada with your Mountain Equipment
co-op it was five million members and a
group in the States called recreational
equipment initiative and ink around the
widgets thirteen million members and
then in Britain the John Lewis
Partnership and Waitrose yeah they're
staffing is a hundred thousand members
of the of the trust so we're saying each
one of those could become issues of its
own money and crack open the
co-operative community which is one of
the least cooperative communities I've
ever dealt with I don't know about your
experience but cooperative movement is
an oxymoron twice they don't cooperate
and they don't move but I understand why
I mean there are a resistive defensive
Network struggling against the forces of
rapacious capitalism yeah you invite
them to relax and enjoy it and then they
don't know what I mean so John Lewis
Partnership or Mac or are you should be
able to go to their website and when you
go to the checkout
there should be a checkout button that
says do you want 30% of this purchase to
go to my seniors home where are an
indigenous youth thing or malaria nets
wherever you know take the bosses now
it's the thing I'm trying to break out
in people's understanding is that that
is a very good business proposition for
Mac Mac makes money hand over fist by
giving away cash and validating its own
currency and the more businesses that
realize that by this persistent linkages
this connectivity the customer staff
network particularly amongst multiple
businesses when you create this this
energization of what is there you're not
pumping something and to make it work
you're enabling the the vitality and the
exchanges between them so that relates
back to your question about the Bible
Mathi how do we get farmers to farm
effectively you make it profitable farm
to farm effectively and that profit
emerges just in the quality of their
soil and their process and the product
because the money works if we try to do
that with the conventional money
we're fighting ourselves all the way
it's it's it's um it's on a slope it
goes down
whereas if we can create this container
this resonant space where people's given
Gant is it's just easy and seamless and
it's inconceivable I know I mean oh my
god so complicated many money's my carbs
my cards but my accounts they're like no
problem to questions but for for anybody
who's been listening it's gonna watch
this and we put it out and was this I
want to learn more about this and I want
to experiment with this in my community
in where would you send them as a sort
of resource website or book to read or
person's work to follow the the first
place to go is check out our software
and try it
the place I'd send for that yeah I've
got to identify an entry point that
would be effective at this point I'll
put a cover page and open money door CC
open money god CC will give an entry
point to whatever is comments with this
process we are in the process of
revising our stuff in a lot of ways
because there's 20 years and websites
and that us finds 25 years of websites
and that's fine plus much more before
that I'm just trying to there's also I
think a uk-based website something like
complimentary alternative currencies not
called UK it has a huge range of did you
know which one I mean can you see I a I
think it's CCI a community currencies in
action it was a European funded report
Leonardo belt and it's it's basically
see so much money was poured into bad
ideas so much expert complexity
confusion you know the Snowden work on
connivin the framework of change and
people brought complicated experts to
satisfy government grant and you ended
up with bad ideas that persisted because
they were funded and had no no
functional output
no no product of any valuable but yet
were supported for various reasons of
conventional wisdom now we need an
unconventional wisdom here I don't know
I did you know I was just I don't know I
was just going to Korea to speak at a
conference on basic income did I mention
that before I think alive email yeah but
yeah okay well explicitly it was out of
my field but suddenly was come
career addresses conference on I said
I'll come but no use for two days I'll
be jet-lagged and stupid so if you can
bring me a week early and stay a week
then I can probably do a few things and
we'll share ideas and whatever and they
they really gave me the red carpet they
set up a workshop with a hundred
government officials currency activists
and academics that was what they said
they were going to do on the fly I gives
a three-hour workshop for you two to run
so I was very excited about that until
the day before I flew they said don't
and that was very disappointing until I
thought damn that's such an opportunity
because if they've gone I would have
made a mess of the presentation my slide
through the works I don't speak Korean
and it means you know who knows you know
that if you don't go you can put all
that time and energy into telling what
you would have done if you had gone yeah
so what I'm doing now is basically
preparing a set of documents and I will
put the link to this on Monday not see
see today's it's a framework that places
the ideas of community currency in the
logos level the logic the theory the
Greek level if you like and then moves
into the Latin of functionality and
activity what you can do as a template
said here's a procedure which with
modification can be applied at the
village the town the city whatever you
know lots of variants in there five
flexibility but it's based upon business
issuing money through covalent to
support community and that's not a
turbine now that's the basic model now
what are we doing with that basic model
ah well what we want to do with the
basic model is it's sort of expression
over the third level is a multimedia
international project of information
education and mutual benefit with
funding available from all over the
world
and focus points for the generation of
basically narratives of change this
sounds so much like it would actually
mean something that would be of value to
that network that is still relatively
fledgling at the moment that was kind of
incubated out of the capital Institute
and with the world under done
regenerative economics it's called the
regenerative communities Network and
it's basically a number of pretty
capable or very capable and committed
players at a regional scale saying we
want to sign up to you at this point
kind of intentional network of creating
an example of a bio regional economic
system and and there they're still
finding their feet with it but some of
them are strong partners like as the
Hudson Valley region which is a very
preaching that is playing with it but in
this part of Costa Rica and and the mom
the users they've generally left
themselves with the difficulty of still
operating in the same model as a
conventional economy so using the token
currency which is I don't think they're
even there yet but what you were just
describing this this mechanism by which
they could then engage local businesses
and local charities into a wider
regional regeneration at work to say
that we've just we've got a mechanism
here where people can as they buy commit
to their local region and to social and
ecological regeneration in their region
this range of charities that they
already residential and that it sounds
really powerful and I'll put you in
touch with Stuart Cohen too because I
think you love to chat with these people
and you've got the gist of it very
accurately you write on it right on the
money one might save it and return your
attention to the specifics that in this
portfolio of local resources hmm it
could be a whole host of
academic artistic individuals you know
this person needs a year off to write a
play this person's doing this this
person needs to go and study that and
they could be equally funded what I'm
calling a cooperative patreon a cult
patronage that's needed yeah I mean it's
no different from patreon accepted
instead of being offered a t-shirt or
the five or six options you you know all
of which tend to drag down the
beneficiary a bit of a cost on the
benefit yeah if it was just you put you
know 500 bucks behind this guy and you
get $500 that work in these businesses
when I finally caved just less than two
weeks ago and set up my friend because
of this situation just making it
necessary for me to some extent and I
really resisted be like I watched all
these videos how do you create your
patreon account it was soon it was all
about incentive and hiding stuff that I
normally share freely behind a paywall
to withhold to get where hole to get
I've gotta say nowhere has got that
religion more deeply than North
Americans and all Europe thinks that way
but Americans believe withhold to get it
so basically I decided to not buy into
that and all my tears that I've set up
what I'm promising people is basically
what I would want to do anyway anyway
yeah a little bit more I would like to
know who that is so they just get a sort
of bunch of an online counsel or even if
they're really high-level supporters
they get get a conversation a month
conversation and so you support that
with an incentivization which creates a
persistent relationship between all the
players and they said persistent
relationship is the capital product and
is that capital product that produces
the soil and
our city and local community and how
would you create that cooperative
picture well our initial site and you
can see this on open money dot org slash
CW open money door org slash CW is the
the model that we've we would still
argue is the way to go but it's
difficult II used to be it needed a lot
of businesses a lot of charities we now
see a direct means of doing it one
business at a time with benefit cash
account accountable benefit on the
balance sheet to the business from doing
this that their accountants will love it
I've got a local CGA who's come out in
favor of what we're doing I mean he
doesn't agree with the business plans
but he agrees with the business
legitimacy of a business issuing its own
money circulates back so the the best
answer would be get half a dozen
businesses like a Rotary Club members of
a Rotary Club or a service group a
Chamber of Commerce to play with the
concept and we have a gaming system you
can download a set of identities cards
and play them out in a real time sort of
simulation in a few hours
representing several months of actual
development because it's a playing that
gives people the shape that allows them
to understand and act if they don't play
they'll stay on the wrong side of the
the dining the word from awful long time
so we gotta get them playing and that
too is play with our software because it
allows you to set up a totally fictional
community in a few minutes you know just
downloaded a spreadsheet of identities
into the accounts of bulk there it is
and then people can log in and play up
the different roles and the thing and
you can chart it on
Kumu graphic output of some sort but
it's it's as immediate and urgent as I'm
afraid the colvett crisis's we're way
behind on development we are underfunded
the materials are effective but they
need an awful lot of additional work to
look as good as the usual contenders so
it's a consciousness experience for
anybody to understand what and why is in
this for them it's best part done by
experience because people don't like the
minute you try to talk your mouth of
explaining it to them they feel somebody
is selling something to them and why
should I end the process of the ego-mind
so so I think we we probably better
bring that to a close otherwise nobody
watch any of it it's true I really
appreciate this Dino I'm going to say I
spent a long time looking for this
conversation and a lot of respect for
your structure and design and your you
writing your videos working I just want
to see it working better I really want
to put thank you see that's that's I'll
do my best and maybe maybe we'll have in
a couple of months or so have another
conversation because there's one burning
question that I agree we shouldn't
necessarily dive into now but it's
because it will open up another hour and
a half it's it's that whole group of
cryptocurrencies that everybody is now
inventing and and I I just have a sense
that if we weighed ourselves too much on
it only works if it's on your mobile
phone and if it has a trailer button it
only works if it's a promise which is
accountable the only thing that makes
the money work is
bility or the promising issuer and these
things are so weak zees there's a seeds
group yeah I was gonna ask you about
seeds you like that I like them I like
their intent
I like their the way they've designed it
and I don't think it's going to work
very well in fact I've had conversations
with the lead person and explained that
I think he give better and along under
our mutual commitment relationship
internal soft currencies with the
network between communities in a quasi
token system but to take the tokens into
the community risks the failure of the
community and the whole network by the
failures of those communities so I think
it's a high-risk proposition good ethics
good intent now I can't say the same
from 98% of the other cryptocurrencies
out there they could neither good intent
nor good design they just trap I added
this with all these currencies
these are attendances that I very much
go by what I sense about the people
behind them and that's why without
really having a strong technical
background on this and I wish I could
have it would have the time to take a
deep dive into all these things I know
that the people who are behind holo
chain as sound individuals meaning well
and all the people that are using not
whole a chain but blockchain in the
region network really are trying to do
something of service to people in Planet
the people are the same so whole chain
on open money tie in very nicely holo
changes is a great anchoring process for
validating the the sovereign identity of
your monetary relationship so it's
basically the accounting I would love to
change so much thank you so much for
this time and really nice and stop
recording and then we can say